<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>The Bangalore Python User Group</description>
    <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://bangalore.python.org.in/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 13:06:21 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 13:06:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talks – Jul, 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We had 4 talks in the online meetup of July 2020. The theme decided as a virtue of talks selected was Testing and Code Quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first talk was by Hiral Amodia on Time Complexity using Python. In the process we revisited the different complexities code can take based on input size.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second talk was by Rohit Sanjay on Unit Testing Using Python. He spoke about the virtues of pytest and how it can be exploited to test our code better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The third talk was by Praveen Shirali on Pythonic Interfaces. He spoke about concepts like typehints, metaclasses, composition and also introduced an up-and-coming interface checker library - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ksindi/implements&quot;&gt;implements&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The fourth and final talk of the day was by Abhiram on Code Quality - the principles and the methods. He spoke about, what he considered where the 4 ways in which Code Quality could be segregated and went on to describe how each could be ensured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resources for all of them can be referred here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bangpypers/18-7-2020-Talks&quot;&gt;https://github.com/bangpypers/18-7-2020-Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Online talk was also livestreamed on Youtube and the Recording for the same can be viewed here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eVYdPdvS2nQ&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eVYdPdvS2nQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/07/18/jul-talks/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/07/18/jul-talks/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flask Workshop 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date: 23 May 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We at Bangpypers do workshops every now and then to break away from the monotony of talks (even if they aren’t really monotonous). And this time we requested Vinay Keerthi - a programmer I’ve come to regard as extremely passionate about the art and the trade of programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started at 10.30 AM on the dot on a Zoom call. This was our second Online meetup (no thanks to Covid-19). The original plan was to wrap up by 1.30 PM but thanks to a rapt audience, the scope of the session and a super-energetic Vinay, we went on all the way up to 4.30 PM! 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was discussed in the workshop?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quick Introduction to Decorators&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction to Flask&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding Routes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Debugging Flask with VS Code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flask Modularization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding a Database&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a Front End&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing a Large Application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As vast as this scope seemed, Vinay made it extremely easy to follow and also provided a lot of interesting trivia along the way, along with some notes about his mechanical keyboards that some members really enjoyed , links to some interesting libraries that make the coder’s journey a lot more fun and easier and also, his lovely pup Subbi 🙂.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Missed the workshop? No worries, you can catch up completely with the notes listed here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bangpypers/23-05-2020-flask-workshop&quot;&gt;https://github.com/bangpypers/23-05-2020-flask-workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also recorded and uploaded to Youtube. Catch it here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1C7Oj0KEhgo&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1C7Oj0KEhgo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Vinay , and all of you who attended and made this a smashing workshop! 😇&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/05/23/flask-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/05/23/flask-workshop/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The 100th Bangpypers Meetup</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date: 22nd Feb 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Venue : VISA Inc, Bangalore&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planning for this had started way back in October or November of 2019 when we first got in touch with Vinay from Visa Inc. They were very passionate about having something to do on the Community front for Python and we at Bangpypers had our 100th meetup in the offing. So, preparations began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We (Anirudh, Ritesh and I) toyed with a lot of ideas before zeroing in on the final agenda (And even that would go through unimagined changes on the D-Day, but what can you do 🤓 )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The final agenda that happened -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bangpypers/Visa Introduction and settling down&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Talk 1 - Anand Pillai - “Memoirs”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Anand Chitipothu - “A Python Magic Show”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abdul M Raja - “Interpretable ML with Python&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lunch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kartik (VISA) - “CPython”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open house session (from Pyladies and Pydata)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workshop - Data Science - Sasidhar Donaparthi&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Closing Remarks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand B Pillai, who started Bangpypers in 2005 spoke about the initial days and gave a stellar talk on the distribution of most active members on the Bangpypers mailing list and the timeline since 2005. He mainly used pandas and networkx in the demo and the talk was somewhat telling of users’ behavior over time in terms of using mailing lists and collaborations and indicated the possible usage of other means of mass communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A detailed post by Anand can be found here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.anvetsu.com/posts/bangpypers-python-100th-meeting-mailing-list-data-wrangling-visualization/&quot;&gt;https://blog.anvetsu.com/posts/bangpypers-python-100th-meeting-mailing-list-data-wrangling-visualization/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was followed by a talk by another early Bangpypers member - Anand Chitipothu. He presented a “magic show” using Python - showing that it was possible to overwrite default functions and operations and also making the audience reverse-engineer the results he was displaying. It was a very interactive session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code repo for Anand C’s session can be found here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/anandology/python-magic-show&quot;&gt;https://github.com/anandology/python-magic-show&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Abdul M Raja gave a short but excellent talk about Interpretable ML using Python , where he spoke about SHAP and LIME among other methods. While we don’t have the material he presented, here’s a related talk of his from Pycon India 2019 - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ECFkJLpQqCQ&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ECFkJLpQqCQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason the Lunch section is especially mentioned above is because Visa provided us a stellar lunch and we’d like to thank them for it 😇&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the lunch, we had Kartik from Visa speak about his journey as an open source developer and a core contributer to CPython. It was most inspiring. He can be contacted on Twitter at  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tirkarthi&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/tirkarthi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was followed by Pooja from Pyladies Bangalore talking about the brilliant community they’ve created and the importance of diversity and representation in a language community. They can be reached at - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/PyLadies-Bangalore-Chapter/&quot;&gt;https://www.meetup.com/PyLadies-Bangalore-Chapter/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last session for the day was a Data Science Workshop conducted by one of Bangpypers’ most eminent regulars - Sashidhar Donaparthi. It was a packed session despite being one of the latter sessions. The material from that workshop is available as a part here - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sdonapar/data_analysis_training&quot;&gt;https://github.com/sdonapar/data_analysis_training&lt;/a&gt; (among other notebooks)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, it was a very successful meetup and very important to us because it was the 100th Meetup for Bangpypers 😇 Thank you all for making it happen!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/02/22/100th-Bangpypers-meetup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2020/02/22/100th-Bangpypers-meetup/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Guidelines for BangPypers Dev Sprints</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;How do you get started on open source programming? How can you contribute to that framework you’ve been itching to add an extra feature to? How do you get guidance and get help pushing your changes to merge upstream?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve wondered on the above at least once, then you’re in dire need to attend one of our dev sprints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Dev Sprint ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Dev sprint is a day long activity where participants work on FOSS projects. The task can be to fix a bug, add a new feature, improve test coverage, write documentation. Participants should bring their own laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re getting started with programming, have been pushing changes upstream for years or just want to brush up your skills, dev sprints are excellent place to interact with the rest of open source programming community and learn about new and challenging problems they’re facing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s beautiful piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://treyhunner.com/2019/04/making-the-most-of-the-pycon-sprints/&quot;&gt;Making the most of the PyCon sprints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for BangPypers, we follow a list of strict guidelines to select the best project for each sprint:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projects need to be in Python.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only those projects with an existing issue/bug lists will be considered. Project issues submitted for dev sprint, should be labelled BangPypers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projects need to have at least 1 maintainer present on dev sprint day for throughout the duration of the event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projects should have a contributing doc. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pallets/flask/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.rst&quot;&gt;An example of contributing document&lt;/a&gt;. If not, we(BangPypers) can help set it up for the project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projects must have a public repository under appropriate open source license. Please do not bring in your enterprise softwares in private repositories. Private repos will not be considered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projects should be actively developed/maintained. We’ll check the Last commits and commit frequency on repo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also label your issues with classifiers like good-first-issue or beginner and intermediate or advanced to make it easier to select issues to work from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Submit your project here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/devsprint20&quot;&gt;bit.ly/devsprint20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guidelines for the participants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your own Laptop with pre-configured needed softwares to get started with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read the description or readme for the project you’re interested in. Go through any and all pre-requisites for the project. Try and setup the project on your system before coming down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge of Git/svn/hg depending on the what the project uses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read and abide by the Code of Conduct that your project might have. Here’s an example of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kennethreitz.org/essays/be-cordial-or-be-on-your-way&quot;&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can I pick up a project ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Please go through list of projects and their issues. If the project is interesting enough, pick the project. If you have any doubts in the project, please leave a comment here and clear your doubt. Please go through the issue tracker and pick an issue to work on. If the issue isn’t clear ask the questions .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry if you feel nervous and all this seems a bit intimidating. We’ll have mentors to guide you every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s some of our previous dev sprints:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/pbxxkqyzcbzb/&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/qxlhwkyvgbvb/&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/qxlhwkytqbzb/&quot;&gt;2015 Dec&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/qxlhwkythbvb/&quot;&gt;2015 May&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/qxlhwkysqbbc/&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get ready for our next &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/kswpqqybcfbcc/&quot;&gt;Bangpypers Dev Sprint of 2020 in March&lt;/a&gt;. RSVP opens a month before the event so that you can study and select your desired project and get acquainted with the mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/12/04/guidelines-for-bangpypers-dev-sprints/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/12/04/guidelines-for-bangpypers-dev-sprints/</guid>
        
        <category>anistark</category>
        
        
        <category>devsprints</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talks – Sep, 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;September 2019’s meetup was held at Visa Inc, Bangalore and the theme was largely about Design - patterns, applications etc. Pursuant to that, the 3 talks that happened were -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design patterns 101 (Ritesh - Software Engineer at Cyware) : 
Slides for Ritesh’s talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slideshare.net/riteshagrawal5036/design-patterns-101-176009891&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design pattern for distributed architectures (Jitendra - VP Engineering at Hotstar) : 
Slides for Jitendra’s talk are available &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1AEicPtrAWRgEpCOXru1RQSNm-c55yAmEJN-BFhY7et8/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Organize your bookshelf using Micropython (Vinay - Sr. Software Engineer at Visa) : 
Content for Vinay’s talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshelfie.gitlab.io&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The site can load a bit slowly because of the amount of graphic content on it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you all for coming and thanks to Visa Inc for giving us the venue for the event and for a scrumptious lunch!! :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be no meetup organized in October, because &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/2019/&quot;&gt;Pycon India 2019&lt;/a&gt; - the largest Python meetup in the country - is happening! If you’re going to be there as well, see you there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;additional-resources-for-you-to-check-out--&quot;&gt;Additional resources for you to check out -&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/faif/python-patterns&quot;&gt;https://github.com/faif/python-patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_Patterns&quot;&gt;Design Patterns - commonly known as ‘Gang of Four’, available on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/buckyroberts/Python-Design-Patterns&quot;&gt;https://github.com/buckyroberts/Python-Design-Patterns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;some-images-from-septembers-meetup--&quot;&gt;Some images from September’s meetup -&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/21_Sep_2019/IMG_20190921_103809.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/21_Sep_2019/IMG-20190921-WA0012.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/21_Sep_2019/IMG-20190921-WA0009.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/21_Sep_2019/IMG_20190921_123251.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/21_Sep_2019/IMG_20190921_110558.jpg&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/09/21/September-meetup/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/09/21/September-meetup/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pycon India 2019 is coming!</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-this-time-its-happening-in-chennai&quot;&gt;And this time it’s happening in Chennai&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/banner-image-bangpypers-2019.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can subscribe to updates about Pycon India 2019 using this &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/GdtTebWL7mn3oKtW2&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;important-dates&quot;&gt;Important dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;btn btn-info&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:2%&quot;&gt;
CONFERENCE
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Oct 12, 13
&lt;br /&gt;Chennai Trade center
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;btn btn-success&quot; style=&quot;margin-right:2%&quot;&gt;
WORKSHOPS
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Oct 14
&lt;br /&gt;IITM Research Park
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;btn btn-warning&quot;&gt;
DEV SPRINTS
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Oct 14, 15
&lt;br /&gt;IITM Research Park
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They are currently accepting proposals for &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/cfp/2019/proposals/&quot;&gt;talks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/cfp/workshops-2019/proposals/&quot;&gt;workshops&lt;/a&gt;. For more details, check out the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://in.pycon.org/2019/&quot;&gt;Pycon India 2019 website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/05/15/Pycon-India-2019-is-coming/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2019/05/15/Pycon-India-2019-is-coming/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>conferences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Code Walkthrough - November 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For November 2018’s session, we planned to introduce something new into our range of things we do. Code Walkthrough, a session where the speaker takes us through the source of a popular library. The meetup started at 10:40AM, with a good decent turned out. OpenEBS sponsored the food and also gave us the venue to host the event. The speaker for the talk was Saptak Sengupta. The session was attended by 53 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saptak started the event with a brief introduction of how Flask came in the first place. He explained the intentions behind introducing the Denied library and how an April’s Fool Joke turned out to be a well-known Python library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, he started the actual code walkthrough, and explained how different parts connect with each other and work. He explained through the major methods used in Flask. Jinja2 and Werkzeug were also covered during the session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a break for 30 minutes in between at 12noon for a networking session. OpenEBS served us with the snacks. The event ended by 1:30PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pics-from-the-meetup&quot;&gt;Pics from the Meetup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/4/5/e/d/highres_476717901.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/4/5/e/e/highres_476717902.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2018/11/17/nov-workshop-report/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2018/11/17/nov-workshop-report/</guid>
        
        <category>bangpypers</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
        <category>codewalkthrough</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talks – October, 2018</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For October 2018’s session, we had a session on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/flmkdqyxnbbc/&quot;&gt;“Data Science”&lt;/a&gt; . The venue was G0-JEK, Domlur and we had 3 speakers. All the sessions ran for around 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first talk by Usha was on “Introduction to Probabilistic Graphical Models” . The talk started with the video by Judea Pearl following which
she gave an introduction to Graphical Models. Further into the talks she
discussed the traditional methods, and how Graphical Models came into light.
This talk consisted of the basics of probability - specifically Bayesian
Probability. Given the complexity of the subject, this will require a follow-up
talk, but the key takeaways of this talk were about the importance of a basic
understanding of probability to understand the topic better. The relevant
Python package is pgmpy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk was by Abdul - a talk on
Introduction to NLP basics, and using it with Spacy. He went over to demo Spacy
using a demo dataset from Kaggle which comprised of the Twitter activity around
JustDoit (Nike) hashtag. Kudos to Abdul, on giving a energetic talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a small networking break, we started off with the next session, where
Divya talked about Language Models using Python. She started the talk from
scratch to discuss Language Models required in NLP as knowledge bases or
referential banks. For example, when a sentence is to be analyzed, it can be
parsed and understand based on the rules and guidelines set by the language
model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The link for the resources would be updated asap&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pics-from-the-meetup&quot;&gt;Pics from the Meetup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/c/7/3/0/highres_475790992.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/c/7/3/2/highres_475790994.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/c/7/3/4/highres_475790996.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/c/7/3/8/highres_475791000.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/c/7/3/6/highres_475790998.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p5&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/e/9/8/7/highres_475799783.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2018/10/27/oct-talk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2018/10/27/oct-talk/</guid>
        
        <category>bangpypers</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talks – Sep, 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For September’s session, we continued the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/BangPypers/events/242065713/&quot;&gt;“Machine Learning/ Deep Learning “&lt;/a&gt; theme. The venue was Synup in Koramangala, and we had 3 speakers. The first two talks were of 40-60 minutes and the last one was around 20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first talk was by Krishna Kant and his talk was titled &lt;strong&gt;“Making Deep Learning Models Robust to Adversarial Attacks”&lt;/strong&gt;. He spoke about how any dataset can be attacked using whitebox and blackbox methods. Whitebox methods such as FGS, an implementation called DeepFool, BFGS and JSMA and Blackbox methods that would basically be using noisy images or adversarial examples generated using the aforementioned methods. He also spoke briefly about defending models against these attacks - using correct classification by training on adversarial examples and rejection of incorrect results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YouTube video for the talk -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/o5oogx&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img.youtube.com/vi/XFEN2zzUSvY/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Adversarial&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Papers and links for reference -&lt;/strong&gt;
http://evademl.org/
https://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.04644.pdf
https://arxiv.org/pdf/1511.04599.pdf
https://arxiv.org/pdf/1707.06728.pdf
https://github.com/uvasrg/FeatureSqueezing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second talk was by Rahul , titled &lt;strong&gt;“Introduction to Reinforcement Learning “&lt;/strong&gt;
Desc –To-Do–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YouTube videos for the talk -&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BcrRethwPjA&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://img.youtube.com/vi/BcrRethwPjA/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;RL&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–To-be-completed–&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2017/09/16/sep-talk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2017/09/16/sep-talk/</guid>
        
        <category>abhiram</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Device Interfacing Workshop – July, 2017</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;BangPypers organized a full-day workshop on 15/July/2017, titled, ‘Device interfacing with Python’. Workshop was conducted by folks from Zilogic Systems, Chennai – Vijay Kumar, Deepak, Babusubashchandar, and Rashid Muhammed – and the venue for the workshop was the corporate office of Treebo Hotels. Intent of the workshop was to initiate the participants on how to use Python programming language to interface with embedded hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Workshop began with introduction to basics of embedded systems, understanding different types of operating systems, quick run through the GNU/Linux OS, then progressing towards hardware interfacing, device drivers, and serial communication, concluding with note on sysfs and how to use sysfs to control hardware. Workshop was a mix of theoritical concepts that preceded the hands-on sessions – Zilogic folks split the tasks of speaking as the slides rolled out for each session and helping the participants as part of the hands-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;embedded-linux-introduction&quot;&gt;Embedded Linux Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepak began this session where he explained the various embedded software models, and the technical differences between firmware, threaded OS, GPOS, and RTOS. Then he proceeded to explain GNU/Linux OS with emphasis on Linux Kernel, it’s design model and the distinction between kernel and user space. This was followed by how files and file systems are managed in the kernel, the layout and the need for file systems. This concept was highlighted using an example of different file system formats including pseudo file systems like proc and sysfs. Linux’s boot process and rootfs was quickly talked through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After touching upon the idea of embedded Linux, it’s pros and cons and the reasons why individuals are inclined to go for it, he explained the specifications and peripheral details of the Zilogic Zkit-ARM-VF51 and DietIO add-on board; this served as the target board for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;device-interfacing-and-introduction-to-device-drivers&quot;&gt;Device Interfacing and Introduction to Device Drivers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus of this session was device interfacing and Vijay discussed two concepts – memory interfacing and device interfacing. He explained how memory interfacing works under the hood i.e. how blocks are addressed in memory and how read and write transaction happens in memory and also, how the same transaction with multiple RAM chips (using decoding logic.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to explain how memory interfacing can be used to do device interfacing via the concept called, memory-mapped I/O. He gave an overview of what memory map is and how hardware devices are mapped as memory addresses and simplified this with examples of using display controller and serial controller. At this point, he mentioned that memory mapped I/O cannot be used for all devices and moved on to the concept called controller based IO where a controller interfaces between the CPU and the device, acting as a translator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was  illustrated with examples like serial controller, I2C controller, and USB controller. The slides and talk were interspersed with tinkering on the target HW by asking the participants to try out code snippets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next major topic began with brief tntroduction to device drivers wherein the speaker explained how the OS abstracts away the differences in the hardware from the applications, using device drivers. Device drivers provide a consistent interface for the applications which is made possible because Unix kernel considers everything as file including physical devices. This presents a similarity in accessing files and IO devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session covered details of how device files work, major and minor mode, and how the kernel uses these modes to invoke the respective driver required by the device. This was emphasized with code examples to show how to read (and interpret) inputs of mouse events, audio playback, read hard-disk partition table – all of this aided by reading from or writing to only device files.  He highlighted the limitations with this approach – it’s not possible to model all device operations, like control and configuration of the device, via reading and writing to files – and how it can be overcome with system call, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ioctl&lt;/code&gt; with live example of ejecting the CD-ROM tray using ioctl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serial-interface&quot;&gt;Serial Interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babu handled this session in which the primary focus was about ‘Serial Communication’. With the short introduction on the internals of UART, it’s cost effective in comparison to communication via Parallel Ports. He highlighted problems like, interference, attenuation caused due to out of board (or band ???) connections and solutions to overcome them. This was followed by a working exampple of a GSM modem listening to incoming text messages whose text was displayed on the LCD of the target HW using Python module, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;PySerial.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I2C’, an acronym for ‘Inter-Integrated Circuit’, a low speed serial bus developed by Philips, was taken up next. Outlining it’s features, like, clock rates, master-slave architecture, he went on to describe the I2C controller and how it’s used to connect I2C devices. Continuing with I2C protocol and how a transaction occurs, the participants, assisted by Babu and the rest of Zilogic folks, tried their hands on accessing accelerometer data and four way key using SMBus – this technology provides APIs for communicating with I2C slave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sysfs&quot;&gt;Sysfs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijay started off this session by explaining about /proc  filesystem, how it was used to obtain system and active processes from the kernel. With the grwoth of complex hardware, it became a necessity to export hardware information to system programs and eventually ‘/proc’ got cluttered with lots of non-process information. And also, the information in ‘/proc’ was not programmatically parsable though it was human readable. And hence, sysfs was born, which is an in-memory file system that exports information from kernel space to user space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With few slides to show the characteristics of sysfs and it’s hierarchy, he explained as to how devices, using /sys/class, are grouped based on functionality and, /sys/bus, where devices are grouped based on their interface. The concepts of sysfs were demonstrated with a simple task involving how to read configuration information of network interfaces, device backlight, controlling radio switches (WiFi) using sysfs. The session ended with a comparison between ioctl and sysfs for controlling/configuring devices, and when to use what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gpios-and-pwm-interface&quot;&gt;GPIOs and PWM interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deepak explained the concepts of binary state high or low with simple devices like LEDs and how GPIOs can be used to switch between either of the two states thus allowing to turn ON/OFF the LEDs. With brief description of how to set the direction of GPIO pins depending on whether they act as output or input, he showed how GPIO interfaces can be accessed from user space applications through sysfs. Participants tried controlling an RGB LED and reading input from key (with the help of sysfs) on the target HW via GPIO pins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PWM, which stands for ‘Pulse Width Modulation’, was lined up next – Deepak explained what is PWM, duty cycle and how they can be used to control the power generated from the source. Session ended with the partcipants attempting to control the oscillations of the piezzon buzzer on the target HW and, the speed of a DC motor , both achieved through PWM using sysfs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adc-interface&quot;&gt;ADC interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Babu took this final session which was about Analog-to-Digital Convertor(ADC) – need for ADC, which helps to convert analog values to digital and why there are hardware devices that generate analog values that cannot be directly consumed by microcontroller(s). He showcased how to read the voltage changes in the Light Dependent Resistor(LDR) on th target HW through ADC using sysfs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BangPypers team is very thankful to the amazing folks from Zilogic for their time and effort in conducting this workshop on embedded systems. We also thank Treebo for hosting the workshop. Hope the workshop participants had great fun and learning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-pics-from-the-workshop&quot;&gt;Some pics from the workshop&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/9/f/3/b/highres_462880763.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/9/f/6/1/highres_462880801.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://secure.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/9/f/6/c/highres_462880812.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;p3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2017/07/15/jul-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://bangalore.python.org.in/blog/2017/07/15/jul-workshop/</guid>
        
        <category>bangpypers</category>
        
        
        <category>meetup</category>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>workshop</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
